Myskania; Records ua800.001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Myskania Records1915-1984
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Myskania
ua800.001
1.42 cubic ft.
The original student government of the State College for Teachers, founded in 1917. Myskania acted as a secret society which selected its own members, but its duties were gradually assumed by the Student Association and it was disbaned in 1979.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Administrative History
In 1915 a petition was submitted to President Abraham Brubacher asking that a student government be organized. In April of 1917, a faculty committee appointed by Brubacher announced the decision to create a student council comprised of seniors. This council would take charge of student affairs and concerns. Soon after, the council adopted the name Myskania, the meaning of which has been kept secret.
Secrecy was to pervade most aspects of Myskania's early history. The organization was self-perpetuating, with senior members selecting their replacements from among the intellectual, moral, and civic leaders of the junior class. Prior to 1931, the student association chose three of its members, but after 1931 Myskania chose all of its own members.
Myskania's role was defined in section 11, article 11 of its constitution: "Myskania shall regulate all undergraduate activities, not academic in nature." These activities included the oversight of student publications, student entertainment, class constitutions, the time and manner of the election of class officers, the organization of the freshman class, and the protection of college traditions.
Myskania's early years saw an active assertion of its powers. In 1921, Myskania suggested the formation of the Student Association as the official student government and even wrote its constitution.
Myskania's eventual demise stemmed from the gradual assumption of its functions by the Student Association. By 1935, the Student Association decided that certain functions, such as the freshman-sophomore rivalries were an executive function, not a judicial one, and thus, Myskania lost one of its main functions. In 1946, due to the disappearance of its governmental powers and the hostility shown to its secret functions and rituals, Myskania announced its dissolution. Later that same year, former Myskania members burned its records and constitution. In 1946, former members of Myskania resurrected it as a volunteer group. It was declared a temporary judicial council in 1946. One year later, Myskania would rise again as an official organization. In 1963, Myskania was called upon to adjudicate the Cortland Case involving the commission of lewd acts by Albany students at a basketball tournament in Cortland, N.Y. Myskania issued summonses, placed some students on probation, and expelled another. This was the last vigorous act ever taken by Myskania. In 1964, one of Myskania's chief duties was taken away, the freshman-sophomore rivalries. Since 1946, Myskania had been allowed only to supervise the function, but now it was not to be involved at all. Under a revised constitution, Myskania's role was to act as guardian of the freshman class and of school tradition, and to screen appointments to the school judiciary. By 1968, the student newspaper was calling Myskania a useless organization that should be abolished. Despite this opposition, Myskania continued to function until 1979, when it appeared before the Student Association to justify its budget. Unable to define an adequate set of functions, Myskania was excluded from the budget. There were no elections to Myskania in 1980. Myskania's own creation, the Student Association, had taken all of Myskania's power, and was thus the main instrument of its dissolution.
As Myskania's basic purpose was to create and preserve school traditions through the control of student conduct and functions, panicularly with regard to the freshman class, the research use of these records would best suit someone interested in development of school tradition, conduct of students, and the development of student government.
Scope and Contents
Myskania survived as an organization from 1917-1979, but in 1946 Myskania declared itself defunct and burned all its records to demonstrate against its lack of power and to preserve the secrecy of the organization, especially the way in which its members were chosen. The meaning of "Myskania" remains a mystery that only its members know.
Collection uncludes bylaws and the constitution, 1928, 1956–63; minutes, 1917–47, 1961–62; correspondence and memoranda, 1962–63, 1978; announcements; and a brief history of Myskania, 1984. Founded in 1917,
The original documents in this collection all stem from the period 1946-79. These records include minutes, announcements, decisions, proposals, tabulations of votes for membership, a membership list from 1917-70 and a history of the organization, written in 1984. The records from the time period of 1946-62 are not very extensive, since during this period Myskania's role had been severely limited.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series.
Student government; Albany (N.Y.); Administrative records; Correspondence; Membership; Minutes; UAlbany Student Groups; State University of New York at Albany
- Copy-Petition by Students for Establishment of a Student Organization, 1915 February 15 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 1)
- Constitution for Myskania, ca. 1928 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 2)
- MYSCANIA: A Restatement of Purpose, 1937 May 20 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 3)
- Minutes of Myskania Formal Initiation, 1941 April 19 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 4)
- Resolutions (Includes Some Student Council), 1937; 1943-1945 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 5)
- Recommendations- Moving Up Day, 1945 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 6)
- Minutes, 1946-1949 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 7)
- History of Myskania (Brief), ca. 1946-1947 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 8)
- Announcements and Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 9)
- Major-Minor Office Plan, 1949-1951 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 10)
- Minutes, 1949-1952 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 11)
- Regulation Governing Freshman Class and Sophmore Replacement Elections, 1950 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 12)
- Announcements, 1951 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 13)
- Decisions, 1951; 1959-1966 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 14)
- "A Committee Report to Rivalry Committee Concerning the Revision of the Inter-Class Rivalry Rules", ca. 1951 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 15)
- Constitution of Student Council of NYSCT, 1953-1955 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 16)
- Student Activity Sheets, 1953-1958 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 17)
- Myskania Pin Donor: John Franklin Orser, 1954 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 18)
- Minutes, 1953-1957 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 19)
- Announcements and Election Tabulations, 1955 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 20)
- Decisions and Tabulations, 1956-1957 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 21)
- Constitution of The Student Association of the NYSCT at Albany- Annotated, ca. 1956 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 22)
- Rules and Procedures, 1957 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 23)
- Procedure For the Enforcement of Traditions at State College, 1957 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 24)
- Student Senate Rulings (Constitutionality of), 1957-1958 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 25)
- Decisions, 1958 (Box 1 (Myskania Records), Folder 26)
- Minutes, 1958-1959 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 1)
- History of Myskania, 1959-1960 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 2)
- Minutes, etc., 1959 April 16-1961 February 16 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 3)
- Potsdam Case, 1960 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1961 March (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 5)
- Minutes, 1961 March 9-1962 February 22 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 6)
- Ideas for Role of Myskania, 1962-1963 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 7)
- Student Senate-Government Reogranization Committee Part 1, 1962-1963 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 8)
- Student Senate - Government Reorganization Committee Part 2, 1962-1963 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 9)
- Cortland Case, 1963 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 10)
- Minutes, 1963 March 14-1964 March 5 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 11)
- Student Senate-Minutes, 1963-1964 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 12)
- Correspondence and Referrals, 1963-1964 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 13)
- Student Senate-Reports, 1963-1964 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 14)
- Role of Myskania, 1965 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 15)
- University Athletics Council-Final Report, 1968 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 16)
- Constitution for Myskania, 1975 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 17)
- History - "The Life and Death of Myskania" by Alfred Basch '31, 1984 (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 18)
- Activities Classification, Undated (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 19)
- Parliamentary Procedures, Undated (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 20)
- The Purpose of Student Government, Undated (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 21)
- Transportation Committee-Rules and Regulations, Undated (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 22)
- Constitution of the Inter-Collegiate Association of the New York State Teachers Colleges, Undated (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 23)
- Constitution of the Student Association of the NYSCT-Proposed Amendments (as revised in Myskania meeting), Undated (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 24)
- Constitution of the NYSCT - Student Association, Undated (Box 2 (Myskania Records), Folder 25)
- Minutes, 1917 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 1)
- Minutes, 1919-1920 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 2)
- Minutes, 1920-1921 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 3)
- Minutes, 1922-1923 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 4)
- Minutes, 1923-1924 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 5)
- Minutes, 1924-1925 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 6)
- Minutes, 1925-1926 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 7)
- Minutes, 1926-1927 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 8)
- Minutes, 1927-1928 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 9)
- Minutes, 1928-1932 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 10)
- In Envelope-Invitations, 1928-1934 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 11)
- Financial Records, 1930-1941 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 12)
- In Binder- Alumni Association with Two Pins, 1930-1941 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 13)
- Minutes, 1932-1935 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 14)
- Procedures, ca. 1932-1935 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 15)
- Contract, 1941 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 16)
- Receipts, 1941 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
- Meeting Minutes, 1943-1944 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 17)
- Receipts, 1944-1945 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 18)
- Constitution of The State College Student Association, 1945 (Box 3 (Myskania Records), Folder 19)